<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<record name="Holders" >

    <section title="Public Records" >

        <header title="The Law" >

            <q>
What are considered public records in N.C. state and local governments?
            </q>

            <an>
				With only a few exceptions, all records created or received by
				officials and employees while transacting official government
				business are public records and must be retained, stored, disposed
				of, and made available for inspection and copying in accordance with
				the law. This applies to records in officials’ and employees’ homes
				and on home or personal computers if the record pertains to
				government business. The public records law is primarily contained
				in N.C.G.S.132-1 through N.C.G.S. 132-10, which is online at:


                <a href="http://www.ncga.state.nc.us/EnactedLegislation/Statutes/HTML/ByChapter/Chapter_132.html" >
					http://www.ncga.state.nc.us/EnactedLegislation/Statutes/HTML/ByChapter/Chapter_132.html</a>.
                <br />
				Public records include paper and electronic documents (including
				emails
				and other electronic messages), photos, videos, maps, computer
				files, computer communications and voice mail messages. Unless the
				purpose and content of a record is personal in nature and not
				related to the transaction of government business, then it is
				a public record and should be managed according to the
                <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/" >
                    Records Retention and Disposition Schedule
                </a> (“Schedule”) that applies to your unit of government (state, university, county or municipal),
				if your governing
				board has adopted this Schedule. If
				your governing board has not
				adopted this Schedule, then you must
				retain all records about your
				government forever.


                <br />
				There are certain records that are exempted from the definition of public records, and there are certain public records that do not have to be disclosed.

            </an>

            <q anchor="whoOwns" >
Who owns public records in N.C. state and local governments?
            </q>

            <an>
Public records and public information are
				the
				property of the people. Government employees and officials are records
				custodians who are responsible for retaining these records and
				making them available to members of the public upon request. 
            </an>

            <q>
Who is responsible for keeping government records?
            </q>

            <an>
The public official in charge of an office is designated to be
				the custodian of records for that office (N.C.G.S. § 132-2).
				Practically, each official and employee is responsible for
				retaining
				the public records in his or her possession. For example,
				if you work
				in a particular department and you send/receive e-mails
				about official
				government business, you’re responsible for
				retaining them for the
				appropriate retention period, unless your
				government has
				established policies that direct others to be
				responsible for
				retaining them.
            </an>

            <q>
Who may request government public records?
            </q>

            <an>
Anyone
            </an>
        </header>

        <header title="Records Management, Retention and Disposition" >

            <q>
Do I have to keep every record I send/receive about
				government business forever?
            </q>

            <an>
				If your governing board has adopted the


                <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/" >Retention and Disposition Schedule</a>,
				then you may likely dispose of
				records after they’ve
				exceeded the retention period outlined in that
				document. However, you
				must retain all records that are subject to
				litigation, audits, or
				that have outstanding requests pertaining to
				them even after they’ve
				exceeded the retention period. You must keep
				these records until the
				outstanding action is resolved. In some
				governments,
				accreditation agencies may require you to keep
				certain records for a
				longer period of time. Always work with your
				supervisor or legal
				staff if you have questions.


                <br />
				If your governing board has not adopted the Records Retention and
				Disposition Schedule, then you must keep all records about
				government business forever. You may not dispose of anything.

            </an>

            <q>
How do I know how long I need to keep records? 
            </q>

            <an>
				Refer to the


                <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/" >Retention and Disposition Schedule</a>,
                which describes the minimum retention period.


                <br />
				It's good to set aside time once a year for records management
				duties (making decisions about what files to keep and purge
				according to the Records Retention and Disposition Schedule).


                <br />
				Remember, records must be retained if there is an outstanding record
				request, court subpoena or court order, some state or federal law or
				grant requirement, if litigation is pending or threatened or if
				there is any other outstanding action pertaining to the record.


                <br />
				Even if the record has surpassed the minimum retention period,
				if it’s an active record that you use in your duties, then keep it
				as long as it’s useful to you.

            </an>

            <q>
How long do I keep emails and other types of electronic messages I
				send/receive about government business?
            </q>

            <an>
				Emails and any other type of electronic messages are just as much
				“official” records as paper records. The content of the electronic
				message determines its record series status, according to the Records


                <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/" >
Retention and Disposition Schedule</a>.
				It’s a good practice to develop
				good electronic message folder
				systems to
				ensure easy retrieval of
				these messages, instead of keeping
				them in
				your inbox and sent box.
				As with your paper records, if an
				email is
				transitory, then you
				likely do not need to retain it once it
				no
				longer has value to you.


                <br />
				You should segregate confidential and protected electronic messages
				from other messages so you don’t inadvertently release them in
				response to a public records request.

            </an>

            <q>
How should I file my emails and other electronic messages to
				ensure easy retrieval when I need them to respond to a record
				request?
            </q>

            <an>
Create electronic message file folders just as you would paper
				file folders. An electronic message file system should follow the
				same philosophy as a paper file system. For example, you may file
				general emails by calendar or fiscal years; you may develop subject
				folder systems, etc.
            </an>

            <q>
What are transitory records?
            </q>

            <an>
				Transitory records are records that are ephemeral, temporary, or
				transient in nature and have only short-term administrative value.


                <br />
				Transitory records are public records, but because of their nature,
				they do not typically have to be retained. Transitory records
				include (but are not limited to) messages with short-term or no
				administrative value, such as many, but not all, voice mails,
				self-sticking notes, facsimile cover sheets that do not contain
				substantive information, and telephone messages. Transitory records
				are created primarily for the informal communication of information
				and not to perpetuate or formalize knowledge. Transitory records do
				not set policy, establish guidelines or procedures, discuss a
				government business matter, discuss a decision, certify a
				transaction, or act as evidence of receipt. (Certified or registered
				mail return receipts that contain important information about the
				names of the sender/recipient and pertinent dates are not
				transitory.) Transitory records may be treated as having a reference
				or administrative value that ends when you no longer need the
				information in the record. Transitory records may be purged when
				their reference value ends unless there is some other reason that
				record should be retained, such as an outstanding record request,
				court subpoena or court order, some state or federal law or grant
				requirement, or if litigation is pending or threatened. However, if
				a record request is received for a transitory record before that
				transitory record has been purged, that transitory record must be
				disclosed.

            </an>

            <q>
What are the appropriate methods of destroying records after the
				time period for keeping those records has expired (according to the
				Records Retention and Disposition Schedule)?
            </q>

            <an>
				If the governing board has adopted the
                <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/" >
Retention and Disposition Schedule</a>, then after records have surpassed
				the retention period,
				you may dispose of them as allowed by
                <a href="http://ncrules.state.nc.us/ncac/title%2007%20-%20cultural%20resources/chapter%2004%20-%20archives%20and%20history/subchapter%20m/07%20ncac%2004m%20.0510.html">
                    N.C. Administrative Code, Title 7, Chapter 4, Subchapter M, Section .0510</a>
				(except those records that
				are the subject of litigation, audits or
				any outstanding actions).


                <br />
				You should shred paper records that contain confidential, protected
				or secure information with a crosscut shredder. You may recycle paper
				records that do not contain confidential, sensitive or secure
				information, as long as the contract with the recycling provider
				stipulates that recycled materials will not be resold as documents
				or records.


                <br />
				If the governing board has not adopted the Records Retention and
				Disposition Schedule, then you may not destroy any of your records.

            </an>

            <q>
Is it okay for me to maintain government records on my personal
				computer?
            </q>

            <an>
				You should not maintain government records on personal computers or
				devices. Maintain all government records on a government
				computer/device. This will ensure that you are never in a position of
				being asked to provide or search personal technology to satisfy a
				records request.


                <br />
				Likewise, it's best to maintain personal records on personal
				devices. If it's important to maintain a personal record on a
				government device for a brief period of time (and if the
				government agency allows this), then create a separate folder for these
				personal records. Delete personal records from the government-issued device whenever they are no longer needed.

            </an>
        </header>

        <header title="Responding to Record Requests" >

            <q>
I've just received a records request. What do I do? 
            </q>

            <an>
				First, adopt a public servant attitude and treat
				records requests as part of your job in government. This
				part of the job is required by state law, which elevates
				the importance of this duty. Do not consider record requests as
				interruptions that prevent you from performing other duties.
				Then, take the next step and put a smile on your face, which
				also will be heard in your voice. Strive to provide excellent
				customer service when asked for public records.
				Second, notify
				the supervisor. It's possible that other employees and
				officials in government have received the same request.
				Good
				communication is critical to ensure everyone operates as
				efficiently
				as possible.


                <br />
				As a courtesy, respond promptly to the requesting party to
				let the person know the request has been received. Ask the person any
				clarifying questions about the records sought. It's also helpful to
				ask if the person has made this request to other staff members as
				well. This will ensure everyone can be as efficient as possible.
				Advise the requesting party that the office will search for the requested records and respond
				by a certain date (and provide that date). Also, let
				the person know of any cost for providing the records (based on the format
				requested). Ask if the person concurs with this plan.

            </an>

            <q>
What CAN’T government employees or officials require of
				persons requesting public records? 
            </q>

            <an>
				You can’t require the request to be made in writing (exception:
				requests for databases may be required in writing). If it’s a
				complicated request, you may ask the requester to put it in writing
				to help you understand it. However, if the requester refuses to do
				so, then you still must fulfill the request and ask clarifying questions to
				make sure you understand the request.


                <br />
				You can’t require the requester to provide his/her name or other
				personal identifying information. Some government offices may request
				that persons requesting records complete a paper or online form.
				It’s fine to ask someone to complete such a form, but your office cannot
				require it.


                <br />
				You cannot charge the requester for “inspecting” records.


                <br />
				For most record requests, you can’t charge more than actual cost to
				produce the record. For example, if it takes an employee one hour to
				produce the records, that employee may not charge for his/her time.
				That employee may charge the cost of the paper required for
				photocopying, the cost of the CD/DVD, etc. If the record request
				will require extensive government resources (overtime,
				contractual services, etc.), then work with your
				supervisors and the person requesting the records to agree on
				decisions for moving forward.

            </an>

            <q>
Searching records to respond to a record request

            </q>

            <an>
				Unless the record request only specifies emails/electronic messages,
				then you must search 

                <b>
ALL
                </b>
 records, including paper and
				electronic.


                <br />
				For emails/electronic messages, it's important to input the
				appropriate search criteria to make sure you are providing, to the
				best of your ability, all records in possession in response to a
				record request.


                <br />
				Let's use the following example. An employee gets a record request
				for all records in his/her possession from January 1 of current year
				through February 28 of current year pertaining to solid waste
				pick-up complaints.


                <ul>

                    <li>
First, remember to check paper files, because the record
						request didn't specify only emails.
                    </li>

                    <li>
Next, think of all the search criteria that might be
						applicable. For example, search for the word "solid waste." It
						would also be a good idea to search for the words "garbage" and
						even "trash.” Don't forget the time period of the request is
						January 1 of current year through February 28 of current year. The
						employee doesn’t need to provide records prior to or after that
						time period to satisfy that request. (It sure is helpful if the
						employee has filed emails in folders according to calendar or
						fiscal years!)
                    </li>

                    <li>
Finally, in responding to the record request, the employee
						should state that he/she has searched the records, and to the best
						of the employee’s knowledge, is providing the records that satisfy
						the request. We’re all human, and humans make mistakes. It’s
						possible that the employee received an email about garbage
						collection, but garbage was misspelled. If so, a key word search
						for the word “garbage” (spelled correctly) would not find an email
						with the misspelled word. The employee didn’t intentionally
						withhold a record, and using the phrase "to the best of your
						knowledge" explains that the employee did his/her best at
						searching for records to respond to the request.
                    </li>

                    <li>
If it's a complex records request, then the employee may also
						want to share the list of key word searches used to search records
						with the requesting party and give the requester an opportunity to add
						additional key words to the search criteria. 
                    </li>

                    <li>
It’s a good practice to close the loop on records request by
						confirming that the requester is satisfied that the
						employee has fulfilled the request completely.

                    </li>
                </ul>
            </an>

            <q>
Providing records in response to a record request 

            </q>

            <an>
				If you have questions about any records being confidential,
				protected or secure or having information in them that may be
				confidential, protected or secure, you should contact legal staff
				prior to releasing these records. For more, see


                <a href="record://holders.protectedRecords" >Protected Records</a>.
                
                <ol type="A" >

                    <li>
If the requesting party has requested emails stored
						electronically, then you can provide them electronically according
						to email system.
                    </li>

                    <li>
						If the requesting party has requested information in paper
						format,
						or if the records the person has requested are only in
						paper
						format, then you might consider one of the following options:


                        <br />

                        <ol>

                            <li>
Make an appointment for the requesting party to come to the
								office and review the paper records. (NOTE: The employee might
								choose to open his/her files for the requested time period to
								the
								person, and it would be the responsibility of the person
								making
								the request to look through these files.) The requesting
								party
								could mark the pages to copy, and the employee would then
								let
								the
								person know the charge for these copies. Once the person
								agreed
								to the charges and authorized the copies, you would either
								make
								the copies at that time (especially if it's a small request)
								or
								let the person know when the copies would be available for
								pick-up (especially if it's a large copy request).
                            </li>

                            <li>
Go through paper files, pull the records that apply to the
								request, and advise the person making the request of the copy
								charges. If the person authorizes copying the records, then let
								the person know when they'll be available for pick-up. If the person
								does not authorize the copies, then he/she may make an appointment
								to come in and review the records and then choose which ones
								they'd like you to copy. Once the person agreed to the charges and authorized the
								copies, you would either make the copies at that time (especially
								if it's a small request) or let the person know when the copies
								would be available for pick-up (especially if it's a large copy
								request).
                            </li>
                        </ol>
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </an>

            <q>
How much time do I have to respond to a record request?
            </q>

            <an>
N.C. law states you must respond within a reasonable amount of time.
				Keeping in mind that this is one way you serve the public and it is a
				job duty required by law, make records requests a priority
				when you receive them. If it’s a simple request that can be 
				accommodated in a few minutes, then do so. If it’s a more complex
				request that will take time, or you have other high priority work,
				then develop an action plan showing when you can fulfill the request,
				and share this action plan with the supervisor and then with the
				requesting party. If the requesting party wants the information
				sooner, then that’s when you have a conversation with the
				supervisor about extensive resources that might be required to
				fulfill the request. Then share information with the requester
				for his/her concurrence, including the cost to the requester 
				if they want the records in a shorter amount of time than
				what is reasonable.
            </an>

            <q>
What do I do if I receive a record request for copyrighted records?

            </q>

            <an>
You may have records that contain copyrighted material and are
				protected by copyright laws. If a request is made for a
				record protected by copyright, then make the record
				available to the requester for inspection. If the requester asks for
				a copy, then point out that the record
				contains copyrighted materials, but allow the requester to copy the
				record himself/herself. Government employees and officials should not
				copy records known to be copyrighted.
            </an>

            <q>
Is a draft record a public record that I must share if I get a
				request for it?
            </q>

            <an>
				Once a draft document has been shared with another, it is a public
				record and is subject to public inspection. Inspection may be
				required for some uncirculated drafts. Consult with legal staff
				about the public record status of a draft document prior to denying
				inspection of that document.


                <br />
				To avoid misunderstandings that can sometimes arise from public
				circulation of discussion drafts, consider labeling each page of
				draft documents that you circulate to others with "DISCUSSION DRAFT
				ONLY."

            </an>

            <q>
How do I know what to charge for producing records for someone?

            </q>

            <an>
				The law permits governments to charge a fee for reproducing a
				record that recovers the actual cost of duplicating the record. Some
				governments may include these fees as part of their fiscal
				year budgets. An estimate of the charges should be given to the
				requester and the requester’s approval obtained prior to reproducing
				records.


                <br />
				In rare cases, providing public records may require extensive use of
				information technology resources or clerical and/or supervisory
				assistance. In these cases, the record custodian may assess a
				reasonable service charge based on the actual incurred costs. An
				estimate of the charges should be given to the requester and
				approval obtained prior to reproducing records.


                <br />
				It’s important for government agencies to be consistent and equitable 
				with the fees charged for reproducing
				records. Do not charge different amounts on a person-by-person
				basis.

            </an>

            <q>
Do I charge someone for providing records on a CD/DVD? 
            </q>

            <an>
You may recover the cost of the CD/DVD.
            </an>

            <q>
Do I have to create a record to satisfy a record request if a
				record doesn't already exist?
            </q>

            <an>
You do not have to create a new record to satisfy a record
				request. Instead, you may respond that no record
				satisfies the request.
            </an>

            <q>
Am I allowed to deny a record request?
            </q>

            <an>
Yes, under certain circumstances (i.e., the record may be
				protected, etc.). Always consult with legal staff before denying a
				record request.
            </an>
        </header>

        <header title="Protected Records" >

            <q>
How do I know that a record is protected and shouldn't be shared
				with others?
            </q>

            <an>
				A protected record is a record that is exempted from the definition
				of public records and a record for which there is statutory or other
				authority permitting or requiring that the information not be
				disclosed.


                <br />
				Protected records should not be disclosed, and in some cases must
				not be disclosed, without the permission of the official custodian
				or legal staff. Just as you have a duty to disclose public records,
				you have a duty to protect the privacy of protected records. For
				example, a Social Security number must never be released as part
				of a public record. Make efforts not to include protected
				information and public information in the same record. Records that
				contain a mix of public records and protected records must be
				disclosed, but the protected information must first be removed (if
				on a separate page) or redacted (if on the same page with public
				information). When in doubt if a record is a protected record,
				consult with legal staff. Consulting with the attorney has
				advantages in the event you determine the record is protected, you
				do not disclose it, and there is a legal challenge.

            </an>

            <q>
What are some examples of records that are exempted from public
				records?
            </q>

            <an>

                <ul>

                    <li>
Confidential communications from the attorney to the client
						within the scope of the attorney-client relationship, as defined in


                        <a href="record://laws.publicRecordsLaw.132" >N.C.G.S. 132-1.1</a>
						(that become public records in three years).
                    </li>

                    <li>
Public enterprise billing information, as provided in N.C.G.S.
						132-1.1. 
                    </li>

                    <li>
Controlled substances reporting system information, as provided
						in N.C.G.S. 132-1.1 (which may be released only in accordance with
						The Controlled Substances Act).
                    </li>

                    <li>
Criminal investigation records and records of criminal
						intelligence information, as provided in N.C.G.S. 132-1.4 (note
						that certain information pertaining to violations of the law and
						arrests and indictments, and certain content of '911' calls are
						public records). Note also that certain information about
						violations or apparent violations of the law is a public record
						pursuant to N.C.G.S. 132-1.4(c).
                    </li>

                    <li>
911 database information, if required by agreement with the
						telephone company, as provided in N.C.G.S. 132-1.5. 
                    </li>

                    <li>
Sensitive public security information, including specific
						details of public security plans and arrangements, detailed plans
						and drawings of public buildings and infrastructure facilities,
						and certain plans to prevent and respond to terrorist activity, as
						provided in N.C.G.S. 132-1.7, and technology security information.

                    </li>

                    <li>
Certain identifying information of minors participating in a
						park or recreation program, although the zip code of residence is
						a public record, as provided in N.C.G.S. 132-1.12. 
                    </li>

                    <li>
Other records for which statutory exemptions apply.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </an>

            <q>
What are some examples of records protected from disclosure?
            </q>

            <an>

                <ul>

                    <li>
Personnel files of employees, which include any information
						gathered by the local government with respect to an employee are
						protected, except for the specific information that NCGS 160A-168
						requires to be public information.
                    </li>

                    <li>
"Tax information" pertaining to a taxpayer's income or gross
						receipts may not be disclosed, as provided in 


                        <a href="record://laws.publicRecordsLaw.132" >N.C.G.S.132-1.1</a>,
						except as provided in N.C.G.S. 160A-208.1. 
                    </li>

                    <li>
Social Security numbers and personal "identifying information"
						is confidential and unlawful to disclose to the public. If a
						Social
						Security number is lawfully collected, it must be segregated
						on a
						separate page, or as otherwise appropriate, from the rest of
						the
						record, as provided in N.C.G.S. 132-1.10. (See also N.C.G.S.
						132.1.10, N.C.G.S. 75-61 and N.C.G.S. 14-113.20.)
                    </li>

                    <li>
Trade secrets and electronic payment account numbers are
						protected as set forth in N.C.G.S. 132-1.2. (Note that to protect
						a
						"trade secret" detailed requirements must be met.)
                    </li>

                    <li>
The seal of an architect, engineer or land surveyor when that
						seal has been submitted for project approval under Part 5 of
						Article 19, Chapter 160A (Building Inspections) as set forth in
						N.C.G.S. 132-1.2.
                    </li>

                    <li>
Certain "trial preparation materials" are protected as provided
						in N.C.G.S. 132-1.9.
                    </li>

                    <li>
Names and addresses of complaining witnesses to crimes must be
						temporarily withheld if release of the information is reasonably
						likely to pose certain threats to the witness or materially
						compromise the investigation, as provided in N.C.G.S. 132-1.4.

                    </li>

                    <li>
Certain economic development incentives are temporarily
						protected, as provided in N.C.G.S. 132-1.11.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </an>

            <q>
How do I redact protected information in the information I release
				in response to a record request?
            </q>

            <an>
				If a record subject to a record request is a protected record, you
				likely will not have to make that record available for inspection
				and copying. When in doubt if a record is a protected record,
				consult with legal staff. Consulting with the legal staff has
				advantages in the event you determine the record is protected, you
				do not disclose it, and there is a legal challenge.


                <br />
				In some cases, however, a public record will contain information
				that is protected, but the entire record is not protected. In those
				cases, the protected information should be deleted in a manner that
				shows that a deletion was made. For example, if the record is a
				paper record, then make a copy of the record, tape over the
				protected information with white correction tape, then use a black
				painter pen to completely mark over the tape. The marked-up record
				should then be copied and the new redacted copy made available for
				inspection and copying.


                <br />
				If you are providing an electronic record that includes protected
				information that must be redacted, then consider saving the
				electronic document as a new file name, and from the new file, use
				the electronic "cut" feature to eliminate the protected text and
				show in the revised document where text has been "cut." It is the
				record custodian's responsibility to ensure that protected
				information remains protected.

            </an>
        </header>

        <header title="Other Helpful Resources" >

            <q>
What are some other helpful resources?
            </q>

            <an>

                <ul>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.sunshineweek.org/" >
SunshineWeek.org
                        </a>
                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.ncga.state.nc.us/EnactedLegislation/Statutes/HTML/ByArticle/Chapter_143/Article_33C.html" >
North Carolina Open Meetings Law
                        </a>
                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.ncleg.net/EnactedLegislation/Statutes/HTML/ByChapter/Chapter_132.html" >
North Carolina Public Records Law
                        </a>
                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/ef04d580-eee7-4cfe-b2ec-06c26a6f95b9/AG-open-government-booklet-4-8-08.aspx" >
Attorney General Roy Cooper's Guide to Open Meetings and
							Public Records
                        </a>
                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/Top-Issues/Public-Integrity/Open-Government/Understanding-Public-Records.aspx" >
Attorney General Roy Cooper's Public Records Q&amp;A
                        </a>
                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
Attorney General Roy Cooper's Open Meetings Q&amp;A
                        </a>
                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/" >
Records Retention and Disposition Schedule
                        </a>
                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/erecords/default.htm" >
Guidelines for electronic records
                        </a>
                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/erecords/Email_Policy.pdf" >
Email as a Public Record in North Carolina: Guidelines
							for its Retention and Disposition
                        </a>
                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/erecords/Emailchecklist.pdf" >
Email User Guidelines Checklist
                        </a>
                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/tutorial_email_20090910/index.html" >
Managing Your Inbox: Email as a Public Record
                        </a>
						(online tutorial)

                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/MPRlocalgovernment/index.html" >
Managing Public Records, online tutorial and self-quiz

                        </a>
                    </li>

                    <li>

                        <a href="http://www.records.ncdcr.gov/tutorial_erecs_20081027/index.html" >
Managing Electronic Public Records: Recognizing Perils
							and Avoiding Pitfalls
                        </a>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </an>
        </header>
    </section>

    <section title="Open Meetings" >

        <header title="Open Meetings" >

            <q>
What is the public policy of North Carolina concerning meetings of public bodies?
            </q>

            <an>
The North Carolina General Assembly has declared it to be the public policy of North Carolina that the hearings, deliberations, and actions of public bodies be conducted publicly. (N.C.G.S. § 143-318.9)” 
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)

            </an>

            <q>
What are public bodies?
            </q>

            <an>
Groups that are required to hold their official meetings publicly ("public bodies") include government authorities, boards, commissions, committees, councils, or other bodies. The law applies to all these bodies of the State, or of one or more counties, cities, school administrative units, constituent institutions of the University of North Carolina, or other political subdivisions or public corporations in the State. These groups are public bodies if they have two or more members, if their members are elected or appointed, and if they exercise a legislative, policy-making, quasi-judicial, administrative, or advisory function. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.10(b) &amp; (c)” 
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)


                <br />
Also, if an official body appoints a subgroup or committee of the whole, then this group is also a public body.

            </an>

            <q>
What are official meetings?
            </q>

            <an>
An official meeting is a meeting, assembly, or gathering together of a majority of the members of a public body for the purpose of conducting hearings, participating in deliberations, voting upon public business, or otherwise transacting public business. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.10(e)”
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)

            </an>

            <q>
Are all meetings covered? 
            </q>

            <an>
No, the law applies to official meetings of a majority of the body's members -- in person or electronically -- to conduct a hearing, deliberate, take action or otherwise transact the public's business. A court has said "deliberate" means to examine, weigh and reflect upon the reasons for or against a possible decision. Even if a body is only receiving information, that counts. 

            </an>

            <q>
What about conference calls and electronic communication that might be considered deliberating or conducting official business? 
            </q>

            <an>
Conference calls are covered. A chat room meeting or other similar electronic communication would count as an official meeting. A message sent from one member of a body to all of the others would not -- it's like posting a message on a bulletin board. A gray area lies between those two examples. If the others were to reply to a message and then copy each other, and then more responses followed, the "conversation" may constitute an official meeting. 

            </an>

            <q>
Are workshop meetings, agenda meetings, retreats and work sessions covered? 
            </q>

            <an>
Yes. These meetings, in which the board can be informed about matters and discuss them but not take final actions, are less formal than regular meetings but are considered official meetings and are open to the public. Even if the board does nothing but receive information, the meeting is public. 

            </an>

            <q>
Can a board majority gather informally or socially without constituting an "official meeting"?
            </q>

            <an>
Social gatherings are allowed, but boards are not permitted to use these events as an excuse to deliberate outside of the public eye. Meals that a board regularly takes together, for example, are considered official meetings, unless they are strictly social and no business at all is transacted. 

            </an>

            <q>
Can a board chair meet individually, and privately, with each member to discuss a public matter? 
            </q>

            <an>
Yes. However, the law also says a board must not essentially take action through these individual meetings. 

            </an>

            <q>
What kind of public notice is required for official meetings?
            </q>

            <an>
Notice is required for all public meetings. The Open Meetings Law contains detailed procedures that public bodies must follow to give the public advance notice of their official meetings. Requirements differ depending on whether the official meeting is a regular meeting, a meeting other than a regular meeting, or an emergency meeting. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.12”
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)

            </an>

            <q>
What are regular meetings, and what notice is required? 
            </q>

            <an>
Regular meetings are those held at a set time and location on a regular basis. The regular meeting schedule must be maintained in a central location. If the government entity has a website, the regular meeting schedule must also be posted on the website. A public body is not required to set a regular meeting schedule. If it does not set a regular meeting schedule, then its meetings would be considered special meetings.


                <br />
To change the regular meeting schedule, a revised schedule must be filed at least seven days before the first meeting for which it applies.

            </an>

            <q>
What are special meetings, and what notice is required? 
            </q>

            <an>
Special meetings are official meetings that are not emergency meetings, recessed meetings or regular meetings. The law requires boards to give at least 48 hours notice for special meetings, stating the date, time, place and purpose of the meeting. Notice must be posted on a government’s principal bulletin board, if it has one, or the door of the board's usual meeting place. Notice must also be provided to everyone who has submitted a written request for notice (also known as the “sunshine list”) and placed on the government entity’s website if it has one. 

            </an>

            <q>
What are emergency meetings, and what notice is required?
            </q>

            <an>
“Public bodies may call emergency meetings if there are generally unexpected circumstances that require immediate consideration by the public body. At an emergency meeting, the public body may consider only the business connected with the emergency circumstances. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.12(b)(3)”


                <br />
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)
A government entity must notify all news media that have requested notice of meetings of emergency meetings. This notice may be provided by phone or the same communication method used to notify governing board members. Other than municipal government, there is no minimum time period for providing this notice, and practically, the meeting may occur as soon as the members can gather. Municipalities are required by law to provide six hours notice to governing board members.

            </an>

            <q>
What are recessed meetings, and what notice is required?
            </q>

            <an>
A governing body may recess a meeting during the meeting itself (in open session) by stating the date, time and location of the recessed meeting. No additional notice is required for recessed meetings.

            </an>

            <q>
Must public bodies keep minutes of official meetings?
            </q>

            <an>
Every public body is required to keep full and accurate minutes of all official meetings (including closed sessions). Such minutes may be in written form or, at the option of the public body, may be in the form of sound or video and sound recordings. 


                <br />
NOTE: If a governing body’s minutes are maintained in video or sound recording format, it’s important to migrate the media as technology changes. For example, remember the VCR tapes some of us used to watch? How many of us now have the equipment to watch these old VCR tapes? Likewise, how many of us have the equipment to play eight-track tapes (or how many of us even know what they are)?

            </an>

            <q>
What are the civil remedies for violations of Open Meetings Law?
            </q>

            <an>
Any person may bring a civil court action against a public body for past violations or possible future violations of the Open Meetings Law.


                <br />
If the person bringing a suit shows that the public body violated or is going to violate the Open Meetings Law, the court may issue an injunction. An injunction may prohibit a threatened violation of the law, or prevent past violations of the law from recurring. As with the Public Records Law, the Attorney General’s Office has no enforcement authority with respect to the Open Meetings Law. Only a court may enforce this law. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.16(a)


                <br />
Note: While the Attorney General’s Office may answer questions about open meetings issues, it does not have enforcement authority. Only a court may enforce this law.
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)  


                <br />
It’s also important to consider the non-legal ramifications. If government officials or entities violate the Open Meetings Law, they may lose the trust and confidence of the public they serve, and they might end up as the lead story in their local media news.

            </an>

            <q>
Are all public bodies subject to the Open Meetings Law?
            </q>

            <an>
The Open Meetings Law specifies several public agencies or organizations that are not subject to the law. For example, the term public body does not include (1) a meeting solely among the professional staff of the public body, or (2) the medical staff of a public hospital.


                <br />
Further, this law does not apply to grand and petit juries, the Judicial Standards Commission, and the Legislative Ethics Committee among others. N.C.G.S. §§ 143-318.10(c) &amp; 143-318.18”
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)

            </an>
        </header>

        <header title="Closed Sessions" >

            <q>
May a public body ever hold a closed session of an official meeting?
            </q>

            <an>
The Open Meetings Law permits public bodies to exclude the public from certain portions of official meetings. These are referred to as closed sessions. The subjects that may be discussed and the actions that may be taken in closed sessions are listed specifically in the Open Meetings Law, and only these things may be considered during a closed session. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.11”
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)

            </an>

            <q>
What are the permitted purposes for holding closed sessions?
            </q>

            <an>
The Open Meetings Law says that a public body may hold a closed session during one of its official meetings only when a closed session is required to prevent public disclosure of the following types of information: legally confidential information, honorary degrees, scholarships, prizes and awards, attorney-client discussions, location or expansion of businesses (including agreement on a tentative list of economic development incentives that may be offered by the public body in negotiations), contract negotiations, certain personnel matters, and criminal investigations, school violence response plans and anti-terrorism plans.
N.C.G.S. § 143-318.11(a)”
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)  

            </an>

            <q>
When can you close a meeting? Some examples include:
            </q>

            <an>

                <ul>

                    <li>
If you are assessing someone’s medical records.
                    </li>

                    <li>
A grand jury is hearing evidence.
                    </li>

                    <li>
A juvenile is involved.
                    </li>

                    <li>
Trade secrets are involved.
                    </li>

                    <li>
Attorney consultation.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </an>

            <q>
What is the procedure for holding a closed session?
            </q>

            <an>
A public body may hold a closed session only if it first begins an open official meeting after proper public notice. During the open part of the official meeting, the public body must make and adopt a motion to hold a closed session. In making the motion to hold a closed session, the public body must state which of the legally acceptable purposes it is relying upon to justify the closed session. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.11(a)”
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)  


                <br />
If while in closed session, the governing board wishes to discuss a topic that was not included in the motion to conduct closed session, they must go back into open session, state the appropriate motion to include the new topic, and then go back into closed session.

            </an>

            <q>
Is a public body required to have minutes of closed sessions?
            </q>

            <an>
The law requires "minutes" be kept that are "full and accurate" and a "general account" to let a person who wasn't there "have a reasonable understanding of what transpired." A "general account" is intended to provide some sort of record of the discussion that took place behind closed doors, whether action was taken or not. The government entity must make those minutes available for public inspections as soon as the reason for the closed session is no longer valid.

            </an>

            <q>
Is a governing board allowed to vote in a closed meeting? 
            </q>

            <an>
Yes, but the vote must be disclosed in the minutes of the closed session. 

            </an>

            <q>
May a board prohibit its members from disclosing what happened in a closed session? 
            </q>

            <an>
No. Permission to hold a closed session is simply permission to exclude the public; it is not authorization to prohibit those present from disclosing what occurred. However, it may be the expectation of those present at the closed session that they do not disclose what happened, as this may be considered frustrating the purpose of the closed session. A person present at a closed session who discloses what occurred at that meeting may lose the trust of his/her colleagues, which might damage future board working relationships.

            </an>
        </header>

        <header title="The Public’s Rights" >

            <q>
May the public request notice of meetings? 
            </q>

            <an>
The “sunshine list” is any member of the public (including the media) who requests in writing to receive public notice of meetings. The unit of government may not charge the media for public notices, but by law the unit must charge $10 per year for non-media individuals who wish to receive public notices by mail. The unit of government may not charge anyone who receives public notices by email.

            </an>

            <q>
Does the Open Meetings Law guarantee the public's right to speak at official meetings?
            </q>

            <an>
All people and media have the right to attend official meetings of public bodies. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.10(a)


                <br />
However, the Open Meetings Law does not give members of the public the automatic right to speak or participate in an official meeting.


                <br />
In fact, if a person interrupts, disturbs, or disrupts an official meeting, the presiding officer may direct that person to leave the meeting. If that happens and the disruptive person refuses to leave, the person may be charged with a misdemeanor. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.17


                <br />
Note: There is a difference between public meetings and public hearings. Public hearings, which are mandated by statute, generally include a provision for public comment. The Open Meetings Law does not apply to public hearings.
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)  


                <br />
Additionally, state law requires county, municipal and school boards to provide for one period of public comment per month at a regular meeting (state law references 153A-52.1, 160A-81.1 and 115C-51). Outside of this requirement, citizens have a right to attend meetings and listen, but they do not have a right to talk to the public body or participate in its deliberations.

            </an>

            <q>
What are the public's rights to listen to electronic meetings?
            </q>

            <an>
A public body may hold a meeting by conference telephone or other electronic means. If it does so, it has to provide a location and means for members of the public to listen to the meeting. The meeting notice should indicate where the public may listen. The public body may charge up to $25 to each listener to help pay for the cost of providing the location and listening equipment. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.13(a)”
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)  

            </an>

            <q>
What are the public's rights to record and/or broadcast official meetings?
            </q>

            <an>
Any person may photograph, film, tape-record, or otherwise reproduce any part of an official meeting required to be open. Radio and television stations are entitled to broadcast all or any part of an official meeting required to be open. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.14”
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)  

            </an>

            <q>
May public bodies conceal the subject of their actions or deliberations?
            </q>

            <an>
If members of a public body deliberate, vote or take other action on a matter at an official meeting, they must do so in a way that allows the public in attendance to understand what subject is being considered. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.13 (c)
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
)  

            </an>

            <q>
May public bodies vote by secret ballot?
            </q>

            <an>
Public bodies may not vote by secret ballot. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.13(b)”
(Source of information: 

                <a href="http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx" >
http://www.ncdoj.com/getdoc/e1447597-eb6d-44f4-9802-d10420bea7db/Open-Meetings-Q-A.aspx
                </a>
) 

            </an>

            <q>
May public bodies vote by written ballot?
            </q>

            <an>
Public bodies may vote by written ballot as long as the ballots are signed and the minutes indicate each member’s vote. Also, the public must be allowed to inspect written ballots immediately after the meeting. Written ballots may be destroyed after the governing body approves the official minutes. N.C.G.S. § 143-318.13(b)

            </an>

            <q>
What if a large crowd shows up for a public meeting, and the room is too small to accommodate everyone?
            </q>

            <an>
If at all possible, move the meeting to a larger location to accommodate everyone present. If the meeting is moved to a different location, as a courtesy, put a note on the door of the regular meeting room letting latecomers know where the meeting is actually being conducted.

            </an>

            <q>
Are North Carolina courts open to the public? 
            </q>

            <an>
With few exceptions, courts in North Carolina are open to the public. The N.C. Constitution states, "All courts shall be open." North Carolina's federal courts also are open to the public and press. Unlike state courts, federal courts do not permit camera coverage. 

            </an>

            <q>
When can courts be closed to the public? 
            </q>

            <an>
In the 1980s the U.S. Supreme Court concluded that the First Amendment gives the public and press the right to attend criminal trials (including preliminary hearings, jury selection, opening statements, witness examination and closing) unless a trial judge enters an order containing specific written findings. Those findings must demonstrate: 


                <ul>

                    <li>
that closure is absolutely necessary to protect a "compelling" governmental interest;
                    </li>

                    <li>
that no less restrictive measure short of closing the courtroom will suffice to protect that interest; and
                    </li>

                    <li>
that the closure is "narrowly tailored" so that its scope and duration are as limited as possible.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </an>

            <q>
Are there exceptions to the general rule of open court proceedings? 
            </q>

            <an>
Yes, those exceptions are:


                <ul>

                    <li>
Commitment hearings. The N.C. Court of Appeals has ruled that there is no right of access to involuntary civil commitment proceedings. However, commitment hearings for people found guilty by reason of insanity in criminal cases are public and must be held in the court where the original trial took place.
                    </li>

                    <li>
Conference. Any bench conference between judges and lawyers or conferences between lawyer and client are not intended for the public. 
                    </li>

                    <li>
Grand jury proceedings. Federal and state law requires that grand jury proceedings be conducted in private. It is also a crime for a grand juror to release information that is presented to a grand jury. It is not a crime for a news organization to publish the information.
                    </li>

                    <li>
Juvenile proceedings. Once closed as a matter of public policy, juvenile proceedings are now presumptively open to the public and the court must find "good cause" to close a proceeding. No proceeding can be closed if the juvenile requests that it be open.
                    </li>

                    <li>
Sex crimes cases. In cases involving charges of rape, attempted rape, sex offense or attempted sex offense, the court may be closed during the testimony of the victim.
                    </li>

                    <li>
Potential for violence. This law is rarely used and if invoked, it probably would not call for the exclusion of all persons. 
                    </li>

                    <li>
Proceedings involving medical peer review records. This is a recent ruling by the N.C. Supreme Court that held the public does not have a right to access court hearings that concern confidential information relating to medical peer review records.
                    </li>

                    <li>
Trade secrets. Generally a court can be closed while trade secrets are discussed.
                    </li>

                    <li>
Victim's compensation. These take place before administrative law judges who may exclude from a hearing all persons not directly involved in the hearing during the taking of medical and law enforcement information as evidence.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </an>
        </header>
    </section>

</record>