<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<record name="Laws">
	<section title="Laws">
		<header title="Public Records Law">
			<q anchor="132">§ 132-1. "Public records" defined.</q>
			<an>
				<ol type="a">
					<li>"Public record" or "public records" shall mean all documents,
						papers, letters,
						maps, books, photographs, films, sound recordings,
						magnetic or other
						tapes, electronic data-processing records,
						artifacts, or other
						documentary material, regardless of physical
						form or
						characteristics, made or received pursuant to law or
						ordinance in
						connection with the transaction of public business by
						any agency
						of North Carolina government or its subdivisions. Agency
						of North
						Carolina government or its subdivisions shall mean and
						include
						every public office, public officer or official (State or
						local,
						elected or appointed), institution, board, commission,
						bureau,
						council, department, authority or other unit of government
						of the
						State or of any county, unit, special district or other
						political
						subdivision of government.</li>
					<li>The public records and public information compiled by the
						agencies of North
						Carolina government or its subdivisions are the
						property of the people.
						Therefore, it is the policy of this State
						that the people may
						obtain copies of their public records and
						public information free
						or at minimal cost unless otherwise
						specifically provided by law.
						As used herein, "minimal cost" shall
						mean the actual cost of
						reproducing the public record or public
						information. (1935, c.
						265, s. 1; 1975, c. 787, s. 1; 1995, c. 388,
						s. 1.)</li>
				</ol>
				Read all of Chapter 132
				<a
					href="http://www.ncga.state.nc.us/gascripts/statutes/statutelookup.pl?statute=132">here</a>.
			</an>
			<q>So what’s not public?</q>
			<an>
				<ul>
					<li>When a local or state government officials work confidentially
						with an attorney. They call that attorney-client privilege.</li>
					<li>State and local tax information that shows how much a person
						earns in year.</li>
					<li>Billing information about private businesses.</li>
					<li>Address of a person’s home who is participating in the Address
						Confidentiality Program.</li>
					<li>Records of criminal investigations.</li>
					<li>A witnesses name when there is a threat of safety.</li>
					<li>The 911 database which has everyone’s address and phone number
						in it.</li>
					<li>Emergency response plans.</li>
					<li>Homeland security plans.</li>
				</ul>
			</an>
			<q>So where are these public records?</q>
			<an>The State Records Center, across the street from the Governor’s
				Mansion.</an>
		</header>
		<header title="Open Meetings Law">
			<q anchor="143">§ 143‑318.10. All official meetings of public bodies open to the
				public.</q>
			<an>
				<ol type="a">
					<li>
						Except as provided in G.S.
						<a
							href="http://www.ncga.state.nc.us/gascripts/statutes/statutelookup.pl?statute=143-318.11">143‑318.11</a>,
						<a
							href="http://www.ncga.state.nc.us/gascripts/statutes/statutelookup.pl?statute=143-318.14A">143‑318.14A</a>, and
						<a
							href="http://www.ncga.state.nc.us/gascripts/statutes/statutelookup.pl?statute=143-318.18">143‑318.18</a>, 
						each official meeting of a public body shall be open
						to the
						public, and any person is entitled to attend such a
						meeting.
					</li>
					<li>As used in this Article, "public body" means any elected or
						appointed authority, board, commission, committee, council, or
						other body of the State, or of one or more counties, cities,
						school administrative units, constituent institutions of The
						University of North Carolina, or other political subdivisions or
						public corporations in the State that (i) is composed of two or
						more members and (ii) exercises or is authorized to exercise a
						legislative, policy-making, quasi-judicial, administrative, or
						advisory function. In addition, "public body" means the governing
						board of a "public hospital" as defined in G.S. 159‑39 and the
						governing board of any nonprofit corporation to which a hospital
						facility has been sold or conveyed pursuant to G.S. 131E‑8, any
						subsidiary of such nonprofit corporation, and any nonprofit
						corporation owning the corporation to which the hospital facility
						has been sold or conveyed.</li>
					<li>"Public body" does not include (i) a meeting solely among the
						professional staff of a public body, or (ii) the medical staff of
						a public hospital or the medical staff of a hospital that has been
						sold or conveyed pursuant to G.S. 131E‑8.</li>
					<li>"Official meeting" means a meeting, assembly, or gathering
						together at any time or place or the simultaneous communication by
						conference telephone or other electronic means of a majority of
						the members of a public body for the purpose of conducting
						hearings, participating in deliberations, or voting upon or
						otherwise transacting the public business within the jurisdiction,
						real or apparent, of the public body. However, a social meeting or
						other informal assembly or gathering together of the members of a
						public body does not constitute an official meeting unless called
						or held to evade the spirit and purposes of this Article.</li>
					<li>Every public body shall keep full and accurate minutes of all
						official meetings, including any closed sessions held pursuant to
						G.S. 143‑318.11. Such minutes may be in written form or, at the
						option of the public body, may be in the form of sound or video
						and sound recordings. When a public body meets in closed session,
						it shall keep a general account of the closed session so that a
						person not in attendance would have a reasonable understanding of
						what transpired. Such accounts may be a written narrative, or
						video or audio recordings. Such minutes and accounts shall be
						public records within the meaning of the Public Records Law, G.S.
						132‑1 et seq.; provided, however, that minutes or an account of a
						closed session conducted in compliance with G.S. 143‑318.11 may be
						withheld from public inspection so long as public inspection would
						frustrate the purpose of a closed session. (1979, c. 655, s. 1;
						1985 (Reg. Sess., 1986), c. 932, s. 4; 1991, c. 694, ss. 1, 2;
						1993 (Reg. Sess., 1994), c. 570, s. 1; 1995, c. 509, s. 135.2(p);
						1997‑290, s. 1; 1997‑456, s. 27; 2011‑326, s. 8.)</li>
				</ol>
			</an>
			<q>When can you close a meeting?</q>
			<an>
				<ul>
					<li>If you are assessing someone’s medical records.</li>
					<li>A grand jury is hearing evidence.</li>
					<li>A juvenile is involved.</li>
					<li>Trade secrets are involved.</li>
					<li>Attorney consultation.</li>
				</ul>
			</an>
		</header>
	</section>
</record>