<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<record name="Seekers">
	<section title="Public Records">
		<header title="Public Records Law">
			<q>What is a public record?</q>
			<an>The term includes paper records, of course. Correspondence,
				reports, minutes of meetings, hand written notes, phone messages,
				and so forth. But it also includes maps, photographs, audio and
				video recordings, e-mail, databases, and spread sheets created or
				received by a government agency in the course of doing public
				business.</an>
			<q>How do you know which ones are public and which ones aren't?</q>
			<an>Under the state Public Records Law, 
				<a href="record://laws.publicRecordsLaw.132">G.S. 132</a>, 
				every record is
				public unless there's another law that says it isn't. And North
				Carolina courts have said repeatedly that the state public records
				law should be construed liberally. So, until you know better, you
				should assume that any record you want is a public record.</an>
			<q>Do the media have more rights to public records than citizens?</q>
			<an>No, and we don't want any. Everybody has the right to examine and
				obtain copies of almost all public records. And you're not required
				to say why you want the record or what you plan to do with it
				either.</an>
			<q>Whom should you ask for a public record?</q>
			<an>The custodian of a record - generally, the public official in
				charge of the office where the records are located - is the person
				obligated by law to provide access and copies. That's usually the
				person to ask. But, as discussed below, you sometimes may opt to ask
				the agency's public information officer.</an>
			<q>Can they make you go through its public information officer?</q>
			<an>Absolutely not. If the custodian wants to consult her agency's PR
				person or anybody else, fine. But the custodian is still answerable
				to you for your request. Sometimes, for your own reasons, you
				actually may prefer to route the request through the PIO, the agency
				counsel, or someone else who will get you what you want. But that's
				your option, not theirs. The agency cannot interpose any official as
				a gatekeeper who would stand between you and the custodian of the
				record you seek.</an>
			<q>Can an agency require you to put a record request in writing?</q>
			<an>In some cases, they can. Even where written requests are not
				required, however, it sometimes is a good idea to put them in
				writing.
				If it is a complicated request covering, for example, a
				range of
				documents created over a particular time span, addressing
				specific
				subjects, or received or created by specific individuals, it
				might
				be better to put the request in writing.
				In two situations, an
				agency can insist on a written request. A public
				agency may require
				that a request for a copy of computer databases
				be submitted in
				writing, and anyone seeking copies of a geographical
				information
				system may be required to agree in writing that he or
				she will not
				use the record for commercial purposes.</an>
			<q>How quickly must the custodian produce the record?</q>
			<an>The custodian must allow you to examine it "at reasonable times
				and under reasonable supervision" and, if requested, must provide
				copies "as promptly as possible." What do "reasonable" and
				"promptly" mean?
				In some cases, that means today. But those words can
				mean tomorrow, or
				next week. It depends on how much time it takes to
				assemble the
				records you want. Did you ask for the director's expense
				reports for
				January? Or is your request more complicated? Reasonable
				can depend
				on what's going on at the agency. Are the employees
				packing up to
				move to a new office? Are they short-handed and trying
				to respond to
				an emergency? In that situation, the law does not
				require the agency
				to stop what it's doing and produce the record you
				want. On the
				other hand, "reasonable" does not mean whenever they get
				around to
				it. You're not asking them for a favor; you're asking them
				to do
				their job.</an>
			<q>Can you get the information the way you want it, a paper record or
				an electronic record?</q>
			<an>If they can give it to you either way, the answer is yes. The law
				says they must make us a copy "In any and all media in which the
				public agency is capable of providing them."</an>
			<q>How much can a public agency lawfully charge?</q>
			<an>The law requires them to provide copies for "free or at minimal
				cost." In a few instances, copy fees are specified by law. Two
				examples: Clerks of Superior Court are permitted by law to charge $1
				for the first page and 25 cents a page for additional pages. But
				absent a specific law, the fee cannot exceed "the actual cost of
				reproducing the public record or public information." You don't have
				to pay an "overhead" charge. And agencies can't just make up a fee
				-- Oh, I think 25 cents a page sounds about right -- and make you
				pay. It's against the law. The cost of a database ranges from free
				to several hundred dollars, depending on how much programming you
				ask the agency to do.</an>
			<q>When public and private records have been commingled, who pays to
				separate them?</q>
			<an>
				The government.
			</an>
			<q>What you should do if you are unlawfully denied access to a public
				record?</q>
			<an>
				<ul>
					<li>First, talk to them.</li>
					<li>Ask them to cite the law that trumps 
						<a href="record://laws.publicRecordsLaw.132">G.S. 132</a>.
					</li>
					<li>
						Agencies may offer all sorts of reasons for not releasing a
						public
						record. If you are denied, you'll want to ask for their
						authority.
						Say to them:</li>
					<div>
						"North Carolina's public records law, Chapter 132 of
						the
						General Statutes, provides for public inspection and copying of
						most records made or received by state or local governments and
						their subdivisions, regardless of the physical form of the
						record.
						If you contend that the document I have asked for is not
						a public
						record, please advise me of the specific statutory
						authority for
						that position."</div>
					<li>To deny access to the record you have requested, they are going
						to have to have a law that takes the record out of the public
						domain, a law that trumps G.S. 132.</li>
				</ul>
			</an>
			<q>So what's not public? Some examples include:</q>
			<an>
				<ul>
					<li>When a local or state government officials work confidentially
						with an
						attorney. They call that attorney-client privilege.</li>
					<li>State and local tax information that shows how much a person
						earns in year.</li>
					<li>Billing information about private businesses.</li>
					<li>Address of a person's home who is participating in the Address
						Confidentiality
						Program.</li>
					<li>Records of criminal investigations.</li>
					<li>A witnesses name when there is a threat of safety.</li>
					<li>The 911 database which has everyone's address and phone number
						in it.</li>
					<li>Emergency response plans.</li>
					<li>Homeland security plans.</li>
				</ul>
			</an>
			<q>Where are these public records?</q>
			<an>Public records are held in government offices all across the state.</an>
		</header>
		<header title="Fifteen Reasons Officials Might Give"
		    tip="Touch a reason to see if it is valid">
			<q>That's not a public document - it's a "draft" or "working"
				document. It's not finished so it's not "official."</q>
			<an>State law does not distinguish between a "draft" or a "working"
				document and a "final" document. A public record becomes a public
				record when it is created.</an>
			<q>I can't give you those expense records because we asked employees
				to write their Social Security numbers on them, and Social Security
				numbers are not public.</q>
			<an>If the government commingles public and private records, then the
				government must separate them at its expense. That's the law.</an>
			<q>The report is finished but I can't release it because it hasn't
				been presented to board members (or the department head or the
				mayor). </q>
			<an>State law does not require another party to sign off on a
				document. A public record becomes a public record when it is
				created.</an>
			<q>Why do you want this document? How will you use it?</q>
			<an>The implication here, of course, is that if you don't have a
				"good reason" for looking at the record, you can't. Under state law,
				the reason you want the record, or what use you intend to make of
				it, doesn't matter.</an>
			<q>You can't see our jail records - you're not a lawyer.</q>
			<an>Public records are available to all members of the public; there
				are no entrance requirements.</an>
			<q>You can't have that database until it's been verified.</q>
			<an>A public record becomes a public record when it is created.</an>
			<q>You're not going to be able to see that record until our public
				information officer gets back from vacation.</q>
			<an>By law, state agencies are not permitted to channel you through
				their public information officer or anyone else. The custodian of
				the record is responsible for its proper release.</an>
			<q>You'll have to ask the office that created that document; our
				office merely received it.</q>
			<an>With few exceptions any agency that has the record, whether it
				generated it or received it, is obligated to show it to you.</an>
			<q>We're busy. We don't have time to look for those documents / don't
				know who has them / don't know where they are.</q>
			<an>Depending on individual circumstances, a short delay may be
				reasonable, but state law requires that public records be made
				available as promptly as possible.</an>
			<q>You must put your request in writing.</q>
			<an>An agency may require that you to put your request for an
				electronic database record in writing, but the law does not require you to
				make a written request for other records.</an>
			<q>Personnel records are off-limits.</q>
			<an>In fact, parts of a personnel record are public, including name;
				age; date of original employment; current position or title; current
				salary; date and amount of most recent change in salary; date of
				most recent promotion, demotion, transfer, suspension, separation,
				or other change in position classification; agency and location to
				which the employee is assigned.</an>
			<q>We've never given those records out before.</q>
			<an>This is simply not a reason for denying access.</an>
			<q>We can't give it to you because you wouldn't understand it.</q>
			<an>Your understanding or use of the information contained in a
				public record is not a factor.</an>
			<q>You can't have those records because they should have been
				destroyed by now.</q>
			<an>As long as a public record exists, it is public.</an>
			<q>Nope. I stamped "confidential" on it.</q>
			<an>The contents of a public record remains public information
				"unless otherwise specifically provided by law."</an>
		</header>
	</section>
	<section title="Open Meetings">
		<header title="Open Meetings Law">
			<q anchor="whoIsSubject">Who is subject to the law?</q>
			<an>It applies to any public body. "Public body" is a broad term that
				includes any authority, board, commission, committee, council or
				other body of state or local government that has at least two
				members and carries out one of five functions: legislative,
				policy-making, quasi-judicial, administrative or advisory. The law
				covers both elected and appointed boards and commission. It does not include meetings in which only staff participate.</an>
			<q>Are all meetings covered? </q>
			<an>No. Only official meetings. An official meeting of a majority of
				the body's members -- in person or electronically -- to conduct a
				hearing, deliberate, take action or otherwise transact the public's
				business. And a court has said "deliberate" means to examine, weigh
				and reflect upon the reasons for or against a possible decision. If
				a body is only receiving information, that counts.</an>
			<q anchor="whatAbout">What about conference calls and emails?</q>
			<an>Conference calls are covered. A chat room meeting would count as
				an official meeting. A message sent from one member of a body to all
				of the others would not -- it's like posting a message on a bulletin
				board. A gray area lies between those two examples. If the others
				were to reply to a message and then copy each other, and then more
				responses followed, the "conversation" may constitute an official
				meeting.</an>
			<q>Workshop meetings, agenda meetings, retreats and work sessions? </q>
			<an>Yes. These meetings, in which the board can be informed about
				matters and discuss them but not take final actions, are less formal
				than regular meetings but are considered official meetings and are
				open to the public. Even if the board does nothing but receive
				information, the meeting is public.</an>
			<q>Can a board majority gather informally or socially without
				constituting an "official meeting"?</q>
			<an>Social gatherings are allowed, but boards are not permitted to
				use these events as an excuse to deliberate outside of the public
				eye. Meals that a board regularly takes together, for example, are
				considered official meetings, unless they are strictly social and no business is transacted.</an>
			<q>Can a board chair meet individually, and privately, with each
				member to discuss a public matter?</q>
			<an>Yes. However, the law also says a board must not essentially take
				action through these individual meetings.</an>
			<q>Do they have to announce meetings? </q>
			<an>Yes. The requirements vary according to the type of meeting:
				regular, special, emergency and recessed. Special meetings are
				official meetings that are not emergency meetings, recessed meetings
				or regular meetings. The law required boards give at least 48 hours
				of notice for special meetings, stating the time, place and purpose
				of the meeting. Notice must be posted on a board's principle
				bulletin board, if it has one or the door of the board's usual
				meeting place. Notice must also be made to everyone who has
				submitted a written request for notice and placed on the government’s website if they have one.</an>
		</header>
		<header title="Closed Meetings">
			<q>When can you close a meeting? Some examples include:</q>
			<an>
				<ul>
					<li>If you are assessing someone's medical records.</li>
					<li>A grand jury is hearing evidence.</li>
					<li>A juvenile is involved.</li>
					<li>Trade secrets are involved.</li>
					<li>Attorney consultation.</li>
				</ul>
			</an>
			<q>When are they allowed?</q>
			<an>When a board plans to discuss particular issues that generally
				fall into the following categories, they are exempted from the open
				meetings law: confidential information, consultations with an
				attorney, claims or litigation, business location or expansion, real
				property acquisition, employment contracts, certain personnel
				matters, investigations, school violence response plans and anti-terrorism plans. See 
				<a href="http://www.ncga.state.nc.us/gascripts/statutes/statutelookup.pl?statute=143-318.11">G.S. 143-318.11</a>.</an>
			<q>What procedure must be followed?</q>
			<an>The law requires the board to disclose the reason for going into
				the closed session and then vote on it. In addition, if the body
				says it is going to discuss "confidential information" it must cite
				the law that makes the matter confidential. If the body wants to
				discuss pending litigation, the motion must identify the parties to
				the litigation. If officials go into a closed session to talk about
				one thing, can they can't talk about other matters. To broaden the
				discussion, the board must return to open session, disclosed the new
				topic, and vote to return to closed session.</an>
			<q>If a board doesn't follow proper procedure what can you do?</q>
			<an>You can stand up, ask for permission to speak, and object. </an>
			<q>You might say?</q>
			<an>
				<div>
					"North Carolina's open meetings law, Chapter 143 of the General
					Statutes,
					requires that all meetings of state and local governmental
					bodies
					be open to the public unless there is a specific statutory
					exemption authorizing closure. If you contend that this meeting can
					be closed legally, please advise me of the statutory authority for
					your action." 
				</div>
			</an>
			<q>Must they keep minutes of a closed meeting?</q>
			<an>
				Yes. And you can ask to see them. The law requires "minutes" be
				kept that are "full and accurate" and that they provide a "general
				account" to let a person who wasn't there "have a reasonable
				understanding of what transpired." A "general account" is intended
				to provide some sort of record of the discussion that took place
				behind closed doors, whether action was taken or not. The law is
				unclear on how detailed the minutes must be. The board must
				make those minutes available for public inspections as soon as the
				reason for the closed session is no longer valid.
			</an>
			<q>Is a board allowed to vote in a closed meeting?</q>
			<an>Yes, but the vote must be disclosed in the minutes of the closed session.</an>
			<q>Can a board prohibit its members from disclosing what happened in
				a closed session?</q>
			<an>No. Permission to hold a closed session is simply permission to
				exclude the public; it is not authorization to prohibit those
				present from disclosing what occurred. However, it may be the expectation of those present at the closed session that they do not disclose what happened, as this may be considered frustrating the purpose of the closed session.</an>
			<q>What happens if the Open Meetings Law is violated? </q>
			<an>
				Three possibilities:
				<ol>
					<li>A court can issue a declaratory judgment,
						which is a finding
						that a violation has taken place.</li>
					<li>If someone
						seeks an injunction against violations, a court may
						order the public
						body not to violate the law in the future.</li>
					<li>A person can ask a
						court to invalidate an action taken (or
						deliberated) based upon a
						violation of the open meetings law.</li>
				</ol>
			</an>
		</header>
		<header title="Your Rights in the Meeting">
			<q>Can you take pictures or tape record the meeting?</q>
			<an>Taping, photographing, filming, or other types of recording open
				meetings are permitted by any member of the public. Radio and
				television station are allowed to broadcast open meetings.</an>
			<q>Can public bodies hide the subject of their deliberations?</q>
			<an>No. Public bodies must deliberate in such a way that a member of
				the public should be able to understand what they are talking about.
				They may not, for example, refer to secret letters or codes in their
				deliberations. They may, however, refer to items on an agenda made
				available to the public before the meeting as long as the agenda is
				sufficient to explain what the board is discussing.</an>
			<q>What kind of background materials is a board required by law to
				release?</q>
			<an>Enough for the public to understand the subject of deliberations
				and actions. The public is entitled to background materials
				distributed to the board under the public records statute.</an>
			<q>Does a citizen have the right to address a public body? </q>
			<an>State law requires county, municipal and school boards to provide for one period of public comment
				per month at a regular meeting (state law references 153A-52.1, 160A-81.1 and 115C-51). 
			    Outside of this requirement, citizens have a right to attend and listen but do not have a
				right to talk to the public body or participate in its
				deliberations. </an>
			<q>Are North Carolina courts open to the public? </q>
			<an>With few exceptions courts in North Carolina are open to the
				public. The N.C. Constitution states "All courts shall be open."
				North Carolina's federal courts are also open to the public and
				press. Unlike state courts, federal courts do not permit camera
				coverage. </an>
			<q>When can courts be closed to the public?</q>
			<an>
				In the 1980's the U.S. Supreme Court concluded that the First
				Amendment gives the public and press the right to attend criminal
				trials (including preliminary hearings, jury selection, opening
				statements, witness examination and closing) unless a trial judge
				enters an order containing specific written findings. Those findings
				must demonstrate that:
				<ul>
					<li>
						that closure is absolutely necessary to protect a "compelling"
						governmental interest;</li>
					<li>
						that no less restrictive measure short of closing the courtroom
						will suffice to protect that interest; and</li>
					<li>
						that the closure is "narrowly tailored " so that its scope and
						duration are as limited as possible.</li>
				</ul>
			</an>
			<q>Are there exceptions to the general rule of open court
				proceedings?</q>
			<an>
				Yes those exceptions are:
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>Commitment hearings.</b>
						The N.C. Court of Appeals has ruled that
						there is no right of
						access to involuntary civil commitment
						proceedings. However
						commitment hearings for people found guilty
						by reason of insanity
						in criminal cases are public and must be
						held in the court where
						the original trial took place.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Conference.</b>
						Any bench conference between judges and lawyers,
						conferences
						between lawyer and their clients are not intended for
						the public.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Grand jury proceedings.</b>
						Federal and state law requires that
						grand jury proceedings be
						conducted in private. It is also a crime
						for a grand juror to
						release information that is presented to a
						grand jury. It is not a
						crime for a news organization to publish
						the information.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Juvenile proceedings.</b>
						Once closed as a matter of public policy
						juvenile proceedings are
						now presumptively open to the public and
						the court must find "good
						cause" to close a proceeding. No
						proceeding can be closed if the
						juvenile requests that it be open.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Sex crimes cases.</b>
						In cases involving charges of rape, attempted
						rape, sex offense or
						attempted sex offense the court may be closed
						during the testimony
						of the victim.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Potential for violence.</b>
						This law is rarely used and if invoked,
						it probably would not call
						for the exclusion of all persons.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Proceedings involving medical peer review records.</b>
						This is a
						recent ruling by the N.C. Supreme Court that held the
						public does
						not have a right to access court hearings that concern
						confidential information relating to medical peer review records.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Trade secrets.</b>
						Generally a court can be closed while trade
						secrets are discussed.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Victim's compensation.</b>
						These take place before administrative
						law judges who may exclude
						from a hearing all persons not directly
						involved in the hearing
						during the taking of medical and law
						enforcement information as
						evidence.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</an>
		</header>
	</section>
</record>